Last video, I talked about the dot
product, showing both the standard
introduction to the topic, as well as a
deeper view of how it relates to linear
transformations.
I'd like to do the same thing for cross
products, which also have a standard
introduction along with a deeper
understanding in the light of linear
transformations, but this time I'm
dividing it into two separate videos.
Here, I'll try to hit the main points
that students are usually shown about
the cross product, and in the next
video, I'll be showing a view which is
less commonly taught, but really
satisfying when you learn it. We'll
start in two dimensions. If you have two
vectors, V and W, think about the
parallelogram that they span out. What I
mean by that is that if you take a copy
of V and move its tail to the tip of W,
and you take a copy of W and move its
tail to the tip of V, the four vectors
now on the screen enclose a certain
parallelogram.
The cross product of V and W, written
with the X-shaped multiplication symbol,
is the area of this parallelogram.
Well, almost. We also need to consider
orientation. Basically, if V is on the
right of W, then V cross W is positive
and equal to the area of the
parallelogram.
But if V is on the left of W, then the
cross product is negative, namely the
negative area of that parallelogram.
Notice, this means that order matters.
If you swapped V and W, instead taking W
cross V, the cross product would become
the negative of whatever it was before.
The way I always remember the ordering
here is that when you take the cross
product of the two basis vectors in
order, I hat cross J hat, the result
should be positive. In fact, the order
of your basis vectors is what defines
orientation.
So, since I hat is on the right of J
hat, I remember that V cross W has to be
positive whenever V is on the right of
W.
So, for example, with the vectors shown
here, I'll just tell you that the area
of that parallelogram is seven. And
since V is on the left of W, the cross
product should be negative. So, V cross
W is -7.
But, of course, you want to be able to
compute this without someone telling you
the area.
This is where the determinant comes in.
So, if you didn't see chapter five of
this series where I talk about the
determinant, now would be a really good
time to go take a look. Even if you did
see it, but it was a while ago, I'd
recommend taking another look just to
make sure those ideas are fresh in your
mind.
For the 2D cross product, V cross W,
what you do is you write the coordinates
of V as the first column of a matrix,
and you take the coordinates of W and
make them the second column. Then, you
just compute the determinant.
This is because a matrix whose columns
represent V and W corresponds with a
linear transformation that moves the
basis vectors I hat and J hat to V and
W.
The determinant is all about measuring
how areas change due to a
transformation. And the prototypical
area that we look at is the unit square
resting on I hat and J hat. After the
transformation, that square gets turned
into the parallelogram that we care
about. So, the determinant, which
generally measures the factor by which
areas are changed, gives the area of
this parallelogram since it evolved from
a square that started with area one.
What's more, if V is on the left of W,
it means that orientation was flipped
during that transformation, which is
what it means for the determinant to be
negative.
As an example, let's say V has
coordinates -3 1, and W has coordinates
2 1. The determinant of the matrix those
coordinates as columns is -3 * 1
2 * 1,
which is -5.
So, evidently, the area of the
parallelogram they define is five. And
since V is on the left of W, it should
make sense that this value is negative.
As with any new operation you learn, I'd
recommend playing around with this
notion a bit in your head just to get
kind of an intuitive feel for what the
cross product is all about.
For example, you might notice that when
two vectors are perpendicular, or at
least close to being perpendicular,
their cross product is larger than it
would be if they were pointing in very
similar directions, because the area of
that parallelogram is larger when the
sides are closer to being perpendicular.
Something else you might notice is that
if you were to scale up one of those
vectors, perhaps multiplying V by three,
then the area of that parallelogram is
also scaled up by a factor of three.
So, what this means for the operation is
that 3V cross W will be exactly three
times the value of V cross W.
Now, even though all of this is a
perfectly fine mathematical operation,
what I just described is technically not
the cross product. The true cross
product is something that combines two
different 3D vectors to get a new 3D
vector.
Just as before, we're still going to
consider the parallelogram defined by
the two vectors that we're crossing
together.
And the area of this parallelogram is
still going to play a big role. To be
concrete, let's say that the area is 2.5
for the vectors shown here.
But as I said, the cross product is not
a number, it's a vector.
This new vector's length will be the
area of that parallelogram, which in
this case is 2.5.
And the direction of that new vector is
going to be perpendicular to the
parallelogram.
But which way, right? I mean, there are
two possible vectors with length 2.5
that are perpendicular to a given plane.
This is where the right-hand rule comes
in.
Point the forefinger of your right hand
in the direction of V.
Then stick out your middle finger in the
direction of W.
Then, when you point up your thumb,
that's the direction of the cross
product.
For example, let's say that V was a
vector with length two pointing straight
up in the Z direction, and W is a vector
with length two pointing in the pure Y
direction.
The parallelogram that they define in
this simple example is actually a
square, since they're perpendicular and
have the same length. And the area of
that square is four. So, their cross
product should be a vector with length
four.
Using the right-hand rule, their cross
product should point in the negative X
direction.
So, the cross product of these two
vectors is -4 * I-hat.
For more general computations, there is
a formula that you could memorize if you
wanted, but it's common and easier to
instead remember a certain process
involving the 3D determinant.
Now, this process looks truly strange at
first. You write down a 3D matrix where
the second and third columns contain the
coordinates of V and W. But for that
first column, you write the basis
vectors I-hat, J-hat, and K-hat.
Then, you compute the determinant of
this matrix.
The silliness is probably clear here.
What on earth does it mean to put in a
vector as the entry of a matrix?
Students are often told that this is
just a notational trick. When you carry
out the computations as if I-hat, J-hat,
and K-hat were numbers, then you get
some linear combination of those basis
vectors.
And the vector defined by that linear
combination, students are told to just
believe, is the unique vector
perpendicular to V and W whose magnitude
is the area of the appropriate
parallelogram and whose direction obeys
the right-hand rule.
And sure, in some sense, this is just a
notational trick, but there is a reason
for doing it.
It's not just a coincidence that the
determinant is once again important. And
putting the basis vectors in those slots
is not just a random thing to do.
To understand where all of this comes
from, it helps to use the idea of
duality that I introduced in the last
video.
This concept is a little bit heavy,
though. So, I'm putting it in a separate
follow-on video for any of you who are
curious to learn more.
Arguably, it falls outside the essence
of linear algebra. The important part
here is to know what that cross product
vector geometrically represents.
So, if you want to skip that next video,
feel free. But for those of you who are
willing to go a bit deeper and who are
curious about the connection between
this computation and the underlying
geometry, the ideas that I'll talk about
in the next video are just a really
elegant piece of math.